Guide to the Columbia University in World War I Collection
Columbia University Archives
- Series VI: War Records Committee, 1915-1930
  - Subseries VI.3: Alumni Classes, 1917-1920
    - Physicians and Surgeons, College of
      - Correspondence
        - Class of 1899, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 21)
        - Class of 1902, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 22)
        - Class of 1903, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 23)
        - Class of 1906, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 24)
        - Class of 1907, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 25)
        - Class of 1912, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 26)
        - Class of 1913, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 27)
        - Class of 1914, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 28)
        - Class of 1915, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 29)
        - Class of 1917, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - Lists--Classes of 1889-1910, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Subseries VI.4: General Correspondence, 1916-1921
    Contains correspondence with the War Records Committee regarding individual war service of faculty, staff, students, and alumni. Some of this information overlaps with other correspondence in this series. Correspondence is filed alphabetically either by name or by subject. These records also include correspondence with the Adjutant General regarding lists of Columbia men and women who participated in the war effort. Under "Barnard College" is a list of "Alumnae Engaged in Overseas Work." Additional correspondence was found at a later date and thus the two alphabetical lists of A through Z are found here.
    - A, 1918-1920 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - B through Be, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Bi through Bo, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Br through Bu, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Ca through Ci, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Cl through Cra, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Cre through Da, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - De through Do, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Dr through Dw, 1917-1920 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Ea through Fl, 1917-1920 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Fo through Fu, 1917-1920 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Ga through Hal, 1917-1920 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Ham through Hu, 1917-1920 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - I through L, 1917-1920, (3 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 5 to 7)
    - Ma through Mc, 1917-1920 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Me through My, 1917-1920 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - N through O, 1917-1920 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Pa through Pi, 1917-1920 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Pl through Q, 1917-1920 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - R, 1917-1920 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Sa through Sl, 1917-1920 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Sm through Sy, 1917-1920 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - T through Z, 1917-1920, (3 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 7 to 9)
    - A through K, 1917-1921 (3 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Krans, Horatio, 1918-1919, (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 4 to 5)
    - L through P, 1916-1921, (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 6 to 7)
    - R through X, 1916-1921, (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Subseries VI.5: War Casualties, 1917-1930
    Consists of correspondence with family members of deceased faculty, staff, students, and alumni. The War Records Committee inquired about photographs and biographical sketches to publish in a war memorial. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the surname of the individual deceased. Original folders were labeled "Dead."
    - Lists of Photographs of the Dead, 1919-1921 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Barry, Vincent, 1920 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Barry, William John, 1919-1920 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Bourquin, J., 1920, 1930 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Brand, Stanley Oliver, 1920 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Bruce, Parker, 1918-1920 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Caldwell, Eugene Wilson, 1918-1930 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Campbell, Ronald, 1919 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Dryfoos, Arthur D., 1918-1919 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Graziani, Attilio, 1919 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Gudebrod, Frederick C., 1918-1920 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Hays, John Elder, 1919-1920 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Hirshler, Jerome Jacob, 1918-1919 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Jubureck, Charles Cornelius, 1919, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Kalvio, George J., 1919-1920 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Kline, Louis A., 1918-1920 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Leonard, Howard George, 1918-1920 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Millward, James, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Peltier, Paul Desnoyers, 1920, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Pennewill, John M., 1921 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Pinkus, Irving J, 1918-1920, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Ream, Ward Hall, 1920, 1930 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1918-1919 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Sprague, Russell W., 1917, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Stein, Morris, 1918 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Stevens, 1919 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Subseries VI.6: Topics, 1917-1923
    Includes correspondence, articles, lists, and general information on topics such as department contact lists, pacifist replies to the personnel questionnaire, war service lists, and war service report cards. The folder "War Memorial-Specimen Papers" contains articles from the publication "Columbia University War Memorial." The drafts and articles are incomplete.
    - Columbia Alumni and Students Who Have Died in Service, 1919, undated (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Columbia Alumni and Students in Service Lists, 1918-1919 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Departmental Contact List, undated (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Doubtful Cases in War Deaths, undated (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Memorial Volume, 1920, undated (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - General, 1919-1920, undated (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Pacifist Replies to Personnel Questionnaire, 1917-1918 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - War Memorial--Drafts of Articles and Specimen Papers, 1919-1923, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 26 to 27)
    - War Service Lists--General, 1919-1920 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - War Service Report Cards, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 29)
- Series VII: Wartime Work, 1914-1928
  This series contains material on various topics, groups, and organizations related to the war effort. Folder "Division of Intelligence and Publicity" contains a small amount of correspondence and some items such as press releases informing the Columbia community about various military programs. The folder of "General Assemblies" contains material on the General Assemblies held for the faculty and/or the university community to discuss current wartime issues. The folder also contains President Nicholas Murray Butler's, as well as other professor's, addresses to the General Assembly of the Faculty on May 7, 1918. The Ninth Coast Artillery Corps correspondence is mostly in relation to the formation of a New York Guard Columbia Unit, which was the result of efforts by the Columbia University Club. Information on the Citizen's Preparedness Parade and the May 10, 1916 meeting with speaker Major-General Leonard Wood is within the folder "Preparedness." See also the oversized folder "Collections Oversize-World War I Collection-Newspaper Clippings" for the Louvain Library Supplement of the Columbia Spectator from April 5, 1922.
  - Certificates, 1918-1920 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Columbia House--Center for Americanization, 1919 (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Columbia-Presbyterian Unit, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Columbia University Post No. 400, American Legion, 1923-1927 (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - General Assemblies, 1915-1918 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Intelligence and Publicity, Division of, 1917, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Letter to the American Ambassador to Petrograd, 1917 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Liberty Loan, 1917-1918 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Louvain Library Reconstruction Campaign, 1914-1929 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - New York State Military Census, 1917 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Ninth Coast Artillery Corps--Columbia Unit, 1918 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Preparedness, 1916 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Service Lists
    - Alumni Who Won Distinction in the War, 1920, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Committee on Mobilization--Men Who Served by 1916, 1916 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Company "I", undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - General, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Non-Columbia Rosters, 1915-1919 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - School of Architecture, 1918 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - University Farm Bureau, undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
- Series VIII: Publications and Clippings, 1914-1970
  Series VIII contains publications and newspaper clippings regarding the University's participation in the war effort. Also includes articles on related issues such as academic freedom (including the controversy over Professors Beard, Cattell and Dana), student protests to the war, the ban on speaker Count Ilya Tolstoy in February 1917, protests by pacifists, and articles on "draft evaders" (in particular Charles F. Phillips). See also full issues of the Columbia Spectator from March, 1917 in the oversize folder "Collections Oversize-World War I Collection-Newspaper Clippings." Columbia's War Work publication is housed in the oversize folder Collections Oversize-World War I Collection--General along with an anti-war poster and two military maps.
  - Anti-War Pamphlets, undated (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Articles regarding Academic Freedom, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Articles regarding Columbia and the War, 1914, 1917-1925, 1935-1940, 1970, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Columbia War Publications, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - General, 1917 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Non-Columbia War Publications, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Women's War Work Membership Cards--A through Col (Box 18)